Guide to the Transport Workers Union of America and Shirley Quill Photographs PHOTOS.032
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Transport Workers Union of America and Shirley Quill Photographs
1913-2007
1941-1966
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Quill, Shirley, 1918-
Quill, Mike, 1905-1966
PHOTOS.032
1.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize flat file folder and 3 oversize folders in 2 shared boxes.
This collection focuses on the history of the Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), founded in 1934, and Michael (Mike) Quill, its president from 1935-1966, although it also includes Quill family portraits, images of leftist and labor activist, Shirley Quill, who was his assistant and second wife, and snapshots and images of early TWU and CIO leadership and conventions. Highlights include a group portrait of the CIO leadership in 1940 (Joe Curran, Quill, Phillip Murray and John L. Lewis); the Unity Slate Victory party; Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking at the Ghandi Society Luncheon; and Mike Quill's last press conference, and his memorial service.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Transport Workers Union of America (TWU) donated its records to the Tamiment Library in 1985. In 1987 Shirley Quill donated papers related to Mike Quill and his involvement in the TWU to the Tamiment Library. Photographs from both donations were separated from paper records and combined to establish a separate photographs collection. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1985.002, 2011.097, NPA.1997.003, NPA.2001.041, and NPA.2008.028.
Appraisal
No materials were removed from this collection.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged by subject.
Biographical/Historical Note
Much of the Transport Workers of America's (TWU) history centers around the fiery figure of Mike Quill, President of the TWU from 1935 to 1966. Quill, born in Kilgarven, Ireland in 1905, started with the IRT subway as a ticket taker. With the financial support of the Communist Party, Quill, together with Maurice Forge, Austin Hogan, and Harry Sacher, was able to lead a successful organizing drive among New York City transit workers beginning in 1934. With Quill as President, the TWU organized subway, bus, and taxi workers in New York and improved wages and working conditions. When he was elected to the City Council (1937-1939, 1943-1949), Quill also used that position to fight for the transit workers, even when it meant going against the American Labor Party, his base of support. With the consolidation of New York City's subway system under one transit authority in 1941, TWU gained more bargaining power. By 1950, their membership grew to over 100,000 transport workers. In the post- World War II period, Quill split with the Communist Party over a fare increase, and he then joined in the CIO effort to eliminate communist-dominated unions from the organization. By the 1950's, the TWU was the exclusive bargaining agent for New York Transit. TWU also expanded during the 1940s and 1950s to establish locals across the country for railroad and airline workers, utility workers, and taxi drivers, among others. The usual pattern of threatened strike and last minute negotiation was upset in 1965 when Quill led the TWU out on a massive strike. In spite of Quill and other TWU leaders being jailed for refusal to abide by a court order, TWU and New York City reached a settlement. Quill died of a heart attack less than three weeks after the settlement.
Shirley Quill, Brooklyn native and the daughter of Russian Jewish immigrants, was born in 1915 and became active with leftist and labor organizations in the 1930s while in college. She was a staff member of the Electrical Workers Union in New Jersey during the early 1940s. Quill met her future husband, Michael J. (Mike) Quill, in 1943 while helping with his campaign for New York City Council. She also served as Mike Quill's legislative secretary after his election to the city council. Their mutual commitment to union organizing and progressive politics led to a friendship and a long relationship. They married in 1961 (both had been previously wed). After Mike Quill's death Shirley Quill continued to be politically active, particularly in women's causes and New York City West Side Democratic Party politics; she was also instrumental in putting together the Association of Tenants of Lincoln Towers (the 4,000-apartment complex on the West Side of Manhattan, where she lived until her death), and wrote a biography of Mike Quill,Mike Quill, Himself: A Memoir. She died in 1991.
• Quill, Shirley. Michael Quill, Himself: A Memoir. Greenwich, CT: Devin-Adair, 1985.
• Cerra, Frances. "Tenant Group Put Clout to Work." The New York Times. December 26, 1982. Accessed June 14, 2012. http://www.nytimes.com/1982/12/26/realestate/tenant-group-puts-clout-to-work.html
• "Shirley Garry Quill, Tenant Organizer, 76." The New York Times. September 28, 1991. Accessed June 14, 2012. http://www.nytimes.com/1991/09/28/obituaries/shirley-garry-quill-tenant-organizer-76.html
Custodial History
Some of the materials in this collection were most likely compiled by Shirley Quill for the book Mike Quill, Himself: A Memoir.
Related Archival Materials
Transport Workers Union of America: Records of Locals (WAG 234)
Maurice Forge Papers (WAG 106)
Gerald O'Reilly Papers (WAG 105)
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: S. Goldstein Interviews (OH 047)
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: Joseph Gayol Files (WAG 085)
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: Naomi Allen Files (WAG 295)
Transport Workers Union of America, Executive Board Minutes, 1938-1971 (Microfilm, Reel 7452).
Transport Workers Union of America Records (WAG 235 )
Transport Workers Union of America, Scrapbooks, 1933-1949 (Microfilm, Reels 7453/1-11)
Scope and Contents
The images in this collection (which may have been assembled by Shirley Quill when she was writing Mike Quill's biography) document many aspects of the history of the Transport Workers Union through Mike Quill's involvement with that history; it also includes Quill family portraits and snapshots and one professionally documented trip to Ireland by Quill (1963). The collection is strong on images of the early TWU and CIO leadership and conventions. Included are shots of the TWU conventions (1939, 1941, 1945, 1948, 1955 and 1961) and the CIO conventions (1937, 1940, 1941, 1942, 1947, 1951, 1952, 1954 and 1957); a number of TWU locals are also represented. One highlight is a group portrait of the CIO leadership in 1940 - Joe Curran, Quill, Phillip Murray and John L. Lewis. Mike Quill's effective use of the media is also evident by the many shots of him at press conferences and on television programs. One image, for example, shows him with TWU picketers at a television station during the 1953 bus strike. There are some shots of Quill speaking, both while organizing and serving as a city councilman. Quill's break with the TWU leaders affiliated with the Communist Party is documented through photographs of a anti-communism rally in 1948. Other highlights include the Unity Slate Victory party (1950), Martin Luther King, Jr. speaking at the Ghandi Society Luncheon (1963), and Quill's last press conference and the memorial service for him (1966). One folder in the collection features images of Shirley Quill specifically, although she also appears in images throughout the rest of the collection.
Photographic prints.; Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Transport Workers Union of America; Spellman, Francis, 1889-1967; Transport Workers Union of America. Air Transport Division; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Larkin, Dennis; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Hogan, Austin; Haywood, Allan S., 1888-1953; Guinan, Matthew K.; Green, William, 1892-1973; Santo, John, 1908-; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Quill, Shirley, 1918-; Potofsky, Jacob S. (Jacob Samuel), 1894-1979; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Faber, Gustav, 1912-1993; Gildberg, Arthur; AFL-CIO; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.)
- Portraits/Mike Quill, Studio Portraits, In Bus With Son., 1941-1942, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Portraits/Mike Quill, Studio Portraits, at Press Conference Before Last Strike was Called, Memorial Program., 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Quill Family., 1937-1941, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mike and Shirley Quill to Ireland., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Mike Quill and Family in Ireland., 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Shirley Quill., 1922-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Irish History., 1913-1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- New York State Industrial Union Council, First Convention., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Transport Worker Union (TWU) Leadership., 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Conventions., 1939-1948, 1955, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Strikes and Protests., 1940-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO)., 1937-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) International., 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Response to 50 Year Celebration of Subways., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Support of Other Strikes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- American Federation of Labor- Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) - William Green, Mike and Shirley Quill with George Meany/James Carey, Joe Curran., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Local 100., 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Local 101 - Support of IBEW Against Brooklyn Borough Gas Corporation., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Local 163 - Virginia Electric and Power Company., 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Local 206, 208, New Orleans, 225 Clifton, New Jersey., circa 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Local 234 - Philadelphia., 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Local 252 - Long Island, First Annual Dance Negotiations., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Air Transport Division., 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Air Transport Division., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Air Transport Division., 1948, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Railroad Division - Pennsylvania Railroad., 1956, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Taxi Division Local 150 - Local 300., 1944-1947, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Councilman Quill., 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Political Campaigns., 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- World War II, Lobbying for Childcare Funding - Emergency Meat Conference., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Martin Luther King, Jr., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- With the Press., 1942-1965 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Quill's Last Press Conference., Jan 25, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Mike Quill Memorial., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Publication Parties for Memoir of Mike Quill by Shirley Quill., Jun 18, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Quill with Identified Individuals., 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Unidentified Meeting., undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Unidentified Groups., undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Unidentified Friends., undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Signed Robert Kennedy Photograph from Transport Workers Union (TWU) Collection., Nov 1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Oversize Negative, 8" x 10" [possibly Quill's family in Ireland?]., undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Miscellaneous, Snapsnots of last trolley car (Yonkers, New York), Interborough Rapid Transit (IRT) Mechanic Attacked and Injured By Bolice., circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) [Pictorial] Calendars., 1981-1988, 1990-1991, 1995-2000, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Shirley Quill's photograph album of a trip by Quill and herself to Israel., circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Portraits., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Unidentified Events., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Biennial Convention, 9th., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ribbon-Cutting Ceremony., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- General., 1920s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- General., 1930s (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General., 1940s (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General., 1950s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- General., 1960s (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General., 1970s (Box 2, Folder 10)
- General., 1980s (Box 2, Folder 11)
- General., undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- General (Ephemera)., 1947-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Unidentified Blow-ups of Mike Quill and Another Individual at a Microphone Being Interviewed [Oversize]., undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS002, Folder 1)
- Publication Layouts, undated (Box Shared Tamiment OS002, Folder 2)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Atlantic City; First Annual Dinner Dance; Quill Proof [Oversize]., 1940 (Box Shared Tamiment XOS002, Folder 1)
- Transport Workers Union (TWU) Convention [Panorama]., 1939 (Flat-file-folder 1, Tray 3)